[Music]
hello everybody good evening good day to
all of you and welcome to the 78th live
episode of ask abhijit
uh today as well like yesterday i'm
gonna keep it a shorter session about 60
to 75 minutes my throat is still not
very well so
today will be a slightly uh a briefed
session
so let us see who all is there i can say
sakshi priya explorer khushi
sankar shantejas
kingster tanushri
super saiyan tanmay khand samarth dungar
singh johan kaya laksha
and many other people harshit 2.0 beast
singh gugu
good evening good day to all of you
so what questions do we have let us take
a look
let's see what questions we have and
let's get right into it
what's the relation between
consciousness and quantum mechanics we
don't quite know yet
uh we know how to use quantum mechanics
in doing various things but we don't
know what quantum mechanics actually is
what it's telling us what the laws of
quantum mechanics are telling us
whether uh consciousness is a factor in
quantum mechanics we still don't know
these things so
i my answer is i don't know
right what else
um
[Music]
uh how how gandhi ji
gained influence in the congress after
returning to india from south africa
why did everyone obey his orders in
india well that's the million or billion
dollar question how did this individual
who was in south africa for more than 20
years
somehow automatically become so powerful
the moment he reached india
so it's clearly it shows you that the
congress party was
a british creation
all the rulers of the congress party
were well people who were in the good
standing of the british
and mr gandhi also was brought to india
by the british
and essentially parachuted to the
leadership position of the congress
party that's what happened
so it's all about power structures what
were the real power structures in the
congress right
and uh
whom were those power structures
beholden to
so that's how it was so it's essentially
that the entire setup was created by the
british themselves the founder of the
congress party was alan hume
who was british right
and all the leaders of the congress
party
the big leaders of the congress party
top leaders they were all english
educated british educated anglophiles
everything they had they owed it to the
british
right
and so did mr gandhi so essentially
that's what it was so mr gandhi so the
the aim of the congress party was to
give an impression to indian indians
that there is a freedom struggle going
on
and uh
it is a civilized freedom struggle we
don't do violence we don't really do any
real harm to the british
we do all these uh all this tokenism
and that's what it was all about all
about so
you know there's a lot still that we
don't know there is a lot that the
historians refuse to write about and
the truth will
eventually all come out
all right um
okay let's see some other questions what
is this which civilization was alive in
the rest of india during the harappan
era what was the political map of india
india is one single civilization how
many times do you tell you guys this huh
india is one
single
civilization
one o n e one there are no 37 different
civilizations in india
the so-called harappan
civilization is indian civilization
from north to south east to west it's
one single civilization
drill that through your thick skulls
the media will tell you there are
civilizations everywhere killer d
civilization some other civilization
somewhere else chandragupta civilization
every new archaeological site they find
they term it as a
civilization that's what we all end up
believing there is only one civilization
in india repeat after me
there's only one civilization in india
and throughout india's history there's
always been one single civilization
it has had lots of different cultural
manifestations lots of
local manifestations in different parts
of india and it's always been one
civilization it's always been the
worship of the same deities everywhere
you may give the dt a different name
but it's still the same deity
you can call lord shiva something else
in south india and something else in
east india and something else in west
india but it's the same god
the overall
structure
the overall values the overall concepts
the overall everything is the same
so my answer is during the harappan era
there was only one civilization in the
rest of india and all across india which
is indian civilization
okay this is a question i get every week
hundreds of times the great indian
warrior king samudra gupta is called the
napoleon of india despite being too much
older than napoleon
why do these foreign historians frame
history in indian history in such a way
these are eurocentric historians they
see everything from their own
perspective so why don't we see things
from our perspective
is anybody preventing all of us
from seeing things from an endocentric
perspective no we also want to see
things from a eurocentric perspective
unfortunately
so it doesn't matter why they have done
it this way or that way we should see
things from our perspective we know that
samadhi gupta was alive more than a
thousand years before napoleon
right
so we can call nepal in the samut gupta
of india and you know what it is not
right to call napoleon the samadhi gupta
of india samudragupta was a victorious
king
he never lost
he was the hero of a thousand battles
he unified the entirety of india almost
the entirety of india under one
political banner his banner
napoleon lost
for napoleon lost twice terribly
he was a loser
and the samudragupta did a lot for india
from a cultural perspective
from a civilizational perspective
napoleon did nothing of that sort for
the french people yeah sure he gave them
a code of laws and all that stuff but
overall he was a very selfish
self-centered person
everything he did was for his own
personal glory
he had no concept of civilization or
serving the people or any such thing it
was all for me me me me that's all it
was
so it is it is actually wrong to call
napoleon the samadhika of india napoleon
was a much smaller person than
samudragupta right so gupta was a way
greater
person
a way greater emperor than napoleon ever
was
so that's what i can say about this my
dear friends
here we go again
so sogata majumdar says vedic sanskrit
is known as the oldest language in the
world then why maximum modern words are
derived from greek words
which maximum modern words are derived
from greek words please explain give me
one example right
i would like to see some examples of
maximum modern
when you talk about maximum modern words
are you talking about language which
language you're talking about you talk
about french you're going to talk about
german
you're talking about russian
are you talking about hindi are you
talking about swahili
which language are you referring to
if you want to ask a question my dear
friend
please frame it properly and give an
example or two so that i can understand
what you're talking about
so therefore i am unable to answer this
question
okay what else do we have
this is bethesda's what do you think of
tamil's trending say no to sanskrit on
twitter today while they tolerate urdu
universities in karnataka why tamils
hate sanskrit well i
you know what i am not tamil so i don't
know why they hate sanskrit i think it's
all the consequence of everything they
have been taught in the past 60 70 years
they worship individuals like that
fellow eevee what's his name perrier the
period fellow the disgusting
fellow called preparia they worship him
nowadays and it's they worship him
because they are taught to worship him
uh they every year they they garland the
statue of that horrific bishop bishop
caldwell and all the dravidianist
parties they they they
so the entire
uh atmosphere the entire environment in
tamil tamil nadu is very much anti-india
anti-hinduism anti-sanskrit
anti-civilization
right so that's why they hate sanskrit
nowadays these young kids they what do
they know that's what they are taught
that's what their parents teach it that
was that's what the teachers teach them
that's what the media tells them that's
what the politicians tell them
so this is the thing about india today
in indian democracy today
hating your culture hating your nation
is a good thing
that is to be tolerated under freedom of
speech
so that's the kind of india we are
living in today it's a mediocre third
rate india
and uh
so as long as this education system this
system of governance this constitution
these laws they continue india is going
to it's india is going to go backwards
and and you will soon see that in other
states also the same sort of sentiments
are going to start emerging in the
northeast of india you already have that
in certain states which are totally
uh
states that have completely lost their
actual original culture and religion
that have been totally abrahamized they
there they already hate india
they even hate their own ancestors for
for being
non whatever
for for following their own indigenous
culture and religion so that's the kind
of india we're living in today india is
a very soft state separatism is is good
it's a good thing in india
if you express uh contempt for hinduism
and indian culture it's a very good
thing actually nowadays in india
so it's no surprise that you see these
things
and yeah urdu university's urdu is good
because it came from outside of india
right so it has to be good that's how it
is
should india block the malacca strait to
pressurize china considering the fact
that a huge portion of china's trade
happens through the malacca strait the
question is does india have the ability
to
block the malaca strait does india have
the naval fire power to do that
india doesn't
the indian navy isn't that powerful
unfortunately
india's navy is not enough not even good
enough right now to be a proper coast
guard
what is the strength of a navy
how do you quantify
the strength of a navy
do you quantify it by saying we have
these many ships no you may have a
thousand ships but if your ships are
toothless
then they are pointless
right the strength of a navy has only
one
measure
and that measure is the number of
offensive missiles you can deploy at sea
at any given time
so if you look at the chinese
on any given day
they can deploy approximately 1500
offensive missiles on their
navy
the japanese have a similar number
approximately 1 500 or so maybe 1 300 i
would say
offensive missiles the japanese navy can
deploy at any given time so right now
approximately 1300 missiles will be
deployed
so that is the strength of a navy well
let's do a similar calculation for the
indian navy i will not give the numbers
but they are absolutely low
right
and therefore india is not currently in
a position to block the malacca state
straight even if it wants to the
question is let's say you send some
ships there you blockade the the
straight but then what are the
consequences can you indefinitely
sustain such a blockade
does india have the does the indian
navy have the ability to indefinitely
sustain a blockade like that
and the answer is most likely no
and can india deal with the consequences
of locating the strait
let's say you blockade this trade you
successfully blockade it for a week two
weeks one month two months then what
happens
what are the downstream consequences
does india know what the consequences
are we know what the consequences are
can india deal with these consequences
we have to think like that right we
can't say okay let's go and locate it
after that what happens we have to think
we have to look at all the second order
third order fourth order fifth order
tenth order twentieth order effects
of doing such a thing only then do such
a do you actually
consider doing such a thing seriously
and
you wanna pressurize china there are
lots of ways of pressurizing china
but we have to consider all the effects
right before we can even think of it and
as of today i don't think india has the
ability to do it and therefore i would
say india at this point in time at this
juncture should not think of locating
the laka strait
for india to be able to do that we need
it we need to augment the navy
significantly
we need to have at least 50 submarines
we need to have like at least 100 more
warships
and we need to have the ability to
deploy at least at least a thousand
offensive missiles at any given time
then we can think of doing such a thing
all right
okay what else do we have um
mentions the type of rice called
mahasali only found in the mugad region
it's each grain is as large as the black
bean
is this variety of rice still present
and grown somewhere well i am not aware
of it
i know that in the northeast of india
there is a variety of rice that is black
in color or dark purple in color they
make heat out of it
right so it's it's found in uh nagaland
manipur etc and other places also there
is also a kind of rice a variety of rice
which is red in color
in
the so-called northeast of india
and there must have been many other
varieties of rice in india like what
you're mentioning but i am not sure if
this
specific
variety mahasali that you are referring
to it's still
is it still like is it still grown
somewhere i am not sure about it i think
what happened during the so-called green
revolution during the congress regime
was that everything was standardized
india had so many varieties of rice and
so many other varieties of crops that
were all
essentially wiped out and only one or
two varieties of rice were
grown and only one or two varieties of
wheat were grown
as part of the so-called green
revolution which essentially bankrupted
the
the uh
the incredible varieties of various
staples we had the crops that we had
so for instance we had millet
uh we had the crops called jowar bajra
in
indian languages right those were crops
that were staples for thousands of years
and today very few people even have
heard of these crops
so that's what the so-called green
revolution did it kind of made a mess of
india's
agriculture
and maybe many of these varieties
may have gone out of existence
permanently you know because of that i
hope that is not the case but
but my i personally haven't
seen this specific variety of price that
you are speaking about unfortunately
okay let me take a couple of questions
from the comments which i was not able
to answer before
okay the real reason of parsi wealth is
that they traded opium with china many
made crores of chinese lives like hell
ultimate ultimately bankrupted its
economy and made it a british prey when
hindu traders denied that send money
yeah it is uh well known that the parsi
businessman were employed by the british
to
um
to be at the forefront of the opium
trade with china
so the so-called opium wars a very
famous uh
event it's not one war it was at least
two wars
that occurred in the
in the 19th century so what happened is
that the british uh they had defeated
the chinese the british americans and a
bunch of european powers that defeated
defeated the chinese empire
and they were forcing them to uh
purchase opium and other cash
cash crops
in exchange for uh
gold essentially so they were extracting
all the value out of china and in
exchange giving china opium and uh
addicting millions of chinese to this
terrible poison right so that's and and
uh you need manpower to do this so the
manpower was essentially the parsi
traders
that's essentially where how the
policies became so incredibly rich they
had these opium warehouses they had the
opium business the
all the big major parsi trading houses
that you know of today they all started
off in the opium trade in the drug
business
so they have these opium warehouses in
shanghai and other places even the
sassoons
they sassoons who are supposed to be the
great philanthropist etc they were drug
runners
david sassoon had a very big opium
business in
shanghai one of the
i think there's a building called
sassoon house that still stands in
shanghai it's used for something else it
was their their warehouse i think where
they stored
the drug the opium
so that's how these
so-called business people got started
off that's how they derived all their
wealth this is not a controversial
matter this is a matter of record
everyone knows this
so yes what you are saying gotham is
absolutely right
all right
how can we have a sharp mind like you as
you recall so much data so easily
well um
what i mean the reason i recall things
is that i i give always give myself
permission to forget things right so
when i read something i have i know that
if i don't find it interesting i'm not
going to remember it i don't care
i don't have to remember everything i
read i would say more than half of what
i read i actively forget it i say it's
not important i am not interested i will
forget it the second thing is that when
i read something that i find interesting
i make mental connections oh yeah i i
okay i come across this new information
yeah it reminds me of this thing and
that thing in that thing so this creates
these mental connections
so i am doing active reading not passive
reading but just read something and just
go through it no when i'm reading i'm
also thinking
so when i come across a new concept new
idea new information i correlate it
mentally with other things that i know
about that i know of other pieces of
information that i already have in my
mind other concepts other ideas that i
have in my mind i try to link it with
that and i try to ask myself how can i
argue against this for instance how can
i
argue against what is being what is
being said in this book or how can i put
the are the the concept differently or
what can i compare it with so that way i
it creates lots of mental connections
and that's why it's easier to recall
information supposedly i mean
maybe that's that's how it works i'm not
quite sure
but the thing is when you read you have
to read actively don't read passively
you're not watching a movie you're
trying to absorb new information and
understand new ideas
so do it actively and create connections
with other ideas that may already be
there in your mind and if you find this
information whatever you're reading not
interesting
give yourself permission to forget it it
doesn't matter so that's kind of how i
do things that's what works for me i'm
sure everybody is different but try it
this way maybe it may work yeah
okay
what about belief of hitler about irene
race hitler was stupid forget about him
what would be the condition of india
today if india hadn't been invaded by
the foreigners india would have been a
better place
okay what else do we have something
interesting please something interesting
give me some interesting
questions
parito says why elon and nasa want to
bring humans to mars as mars is much
nearer to the asteroid belt and has a
danger of asteroids in earth
where did you get this information that
there's a danger of asteroids there
uh we have never witnessed any asteroid
strike on ma mars and
and yeah it is closer to the asteroid
belt than to the earth but the asteroid
belt is still a huge humongous distance
away from mars
the asteroid belt is roughly between the
orbits of mars and
jupiter
and it's really really really far away
from mars and even if you go into the
asteroid belt it's almost empty
you won't find an asteroid for
kilometers hundreds of kilometers maybe
millions of kilometers around you
that's how it is even the asteroid belt
is very empty so you know this
danger
i mean i'm sure this is what you studied
and learned in school but the danger
that you're referring to is over
exaggerated
so the reason why elon musk let's talk
about elon musk not nasa nasa has never
said we need to bring humans to mass
elon musk keeps emphasizing that so his
logic is that we are messing up the
planet
and it's always good to have
plan b
it's always good to be a multi-planetary
species in case something goes wrong
with one planet we know what happened to
the dinosaurs we know that there was a
either an asteroid strike or a cometary
strike in conjunction with other events
that happened on our planet like the
deccan traps etc
that essentially killed off
a significant majority of the species on
our planet at the time
so we don't want something like that to
happen to us and therefore it always
makes sense to have another planet to go
to and that's why he wants to bring
humans to mars
uh and also because we have this uh
this entire situation going on right now
of climate change and the pollution of
the
atmosphere and the oceans and all that
we may end up ruining this planet and
making it uninhabitable
in that case it's always good to have a
second planet so that's some of the
logic that's going around and that's why
uh
elon musk is trying to make us a
multi-planetary species and
he aims to
send a rocket with human beings to mars
pretty soon maybe in the next 20 years
maximum
okay
where are we where else are we
manu gowda says does city state concept
work good for some indian cities today
see the city-state concept was present
in ancient greece when you had these
city-states
like athens like sparta and so on
but these were independent states
these were like independent countries
but cities city-states
in india we had various ganarajas
republics mahajanapadas etc which are
also small smaller sized smaller scale
republics
but the city-state concept essentially
says that you have independent cities
how will that work for india india is a
is one single nation
right
in in case of some cities like
some cities are so large they have a
population of several million for
instance delhi is an enormous city
kolkata mumbai
many of these metropolitan cities are
their population exceeds that of many
countries actually right
so maybe there's a case to be made to
convert each of these cities into its
own state perhaps
so there is an experiment that could be
tried that would hopefully give better
governance and administration etc
but uh yeah that's what i can say
so in in case of certain very large
metropolitan cities you could possibly
you know do that sort of experiment
and
create a city-state framework perhaps i
don't know
so maybe it could work maybe it would
give better governance it's something
certainly that one can
think of and perhaps
perhaps try it out
what is akashic record well i don't know
what that is
nope i don't know
when mr gandhi
led a protest why was he never injured
why the british tried to stop using
violence was mr gandhi
was mr gandhi on a diet that made him
strong physically no
uh
the british never ever tried to
hit mr gandhi in any way whatsoever
the reason he was never injured is that
because the british made sure he was
never injured he was special somehow to
the british
they had
special affection for mr gandhi
apparently
when it comes to mr lala he was killed
right he was
beaten to death during one of his
protests
and many indians were beaten to death
during
demonstrations and protests against the
british but somehow mr gandhi's protests
were special
the british never ever touched mr gandhi
isn't that
fascinating
all right
um what else do we have
uh
should gandhi's where is it oops should
gandhi's image be replaced with that of
mr bose
and also some
others who also did contribute to the
freedom struggle on indian notes
currency i would say yeah why not why
not mr gandhi wasn't the only one who
contributed to india's freedom struggle
actually he did
well
that's for
it's for you all to judge but yeah
certainly why not mr bose
why not mr bose mr bozek is the man who
really
who actually scared the hell scared the
pants of the british and that's that's
the it's the reason why the british
actually decided to leave
you know because mr bose was so popular
especially among the armed forces the
royal
indian navy the royal
british
army or whatever they called it
and they were so scared they decided to
leave post haste
so it's actually mr bose who contributed
to the hasty
withdrawal of the british from india so
i would say yes
why don't we have mr bose on india's
currency notes why not
i really wonder why it's not being done
after all these years 70 years we still
see the same old face same tired old
face on our currency notes
so i think it's yeah it's certainly time
for a change
of that kind
all right
what else do we have
okay let me take some questions from
okay what is this here this is a long
question
akash says
what is the definition of dharma by
krishna it's so confusing he does things
that rama would never do why both are
contradictory why always every indian
king followed the way of rama and not
krishna not attacking enemies when they
are running away from battle prasira
chawan
etc
it looks like they are following rama's
way if they were following krishna's way
they would never have been defeated
as per me krishna dharma is to go to any
extent do anything do
ultimate intolerance if it establishes
dharma isn't it
what's your view on how krishna
interpreted dharma
see you can make it very complicated or
you can make it very very simple
what krishna
interpreted dharma is is what's written
in the bhagavad-gita right
so the bhagavad-gita is actually
it's quite simple
in two words it is destroy dharma do
whatever it takes to destroy a dharma
that's it
that is the simple message that is given
in the bhagavad-gita
don't over-complicate things
your only duty as a king as a ruler as a
warrior
is to do whatever it takes to destroy a
dharma now we have to understand the
difference between lord rama and lord
krishna right lord rama lived
lord krishna you lived in the dwarf
these are different yugas right
so during the uk they said that the
world was a much better place and
therefore lord rama could
it was okay for him to
[Music]
conduct himself in a more idealistic way
than what lord krishna could afford to
do during the dwapua yoga because the
yoga the things the conditions were
different human nature was different and
the worst jig obviously is today the
kali yuga
so today we have to go even worse
go even beyond what lord krishna said
and uh follow the precepts of vishnu
see even in this astra
the principal duty of the king is to
serve the nation and the people the
highest morality of a king
is that his kingdom and his people
should prosper right that's so again
it's all about service it's it's about
the king's duty is not to ensure to
enjoy life and enjoy the power and money
and all that his
only duty is to serve
the king is a servant his only duty is
to put the nation and the people ahead
of his comfort and his in his in his
pleasure and joy and all that
but the way to do it is different in the
arthashastra in the eartha shasta the
king is enjoined to do whatever it takes
even crooked means even assassinations
even poisonings
even all kinds of other things in order
to succeed in serving the people and the
nation right
so in the threat of you it was different
in the dwarf
it was different and in the
also it was different but the
aim of the king was always the same
the duty of the king was always the same
to serve the people and the nation right
so the definition of dharma by per
krishna is very simple do whatever it
takes to destroy a dharma that's
essentially what the entire mahabharat
war is about and that's what the
bhagavad-gita is about do your duty
forget what whatever
uh
maya you observe just do your duty and
don't worry about the
uh
results
that's what he said to arjun so that's
what i can say in brief
i i like to keep things very simple
all right let us go back to the
questions
um
what else do we have
okay what do we have a history of the
khan title how radio electromagnetic
waves help in astrophysics as they
cannot be visualized
let me answer the first question the
history of the khan title
so today
khan is a very very concerning surname
among the muslim people in the
subcontinent of india
even in iran i believe
so in india pakistan bangladesh
afghanistan etc muslims
many muslims have the surname or title
khan
and they seem to consider it something
of
something that
adds some prestige
to them right and even in iran i think
the title khan or surname khan is used
to some extent
so
so therefore the common belief in india
and other places is that khan is
a muslim surname
but that is not the case
khan is not a muslim surname it's a
mongol title
it means
leader or ruler
all right
and it's not just a mongol title
it is
something even the turks used for the
same purpose to denote leader
so the mongols and the turks they have a
common origin and their ancestors were
called the hunnic peoples the huns
and we indians also had
we had many encounters with the hoans
uh
so their
native culture religion whatever you
know whatever you want to call it is
called tangerism in english thingism so
the principle deity is the the sky god
called thangri and the mother goddess
called umai i believe she's called umai
and there's a whole other pantheon of
minor gods and deities and all so it's a
polytheistic culture
so tangerism is what it's it's called in
the west and in english so it is a
culture that was common to the turkic
peoples and the mongolian peoples and
their ancestors the
peoples
and therefore uh
the
original turkic language is also very
similar to the original mongol language
in fact when turkey became independent
the father of the nation mustafa kemal
ataturk he ordered that all arabic words
be removed from turkish and the
equivalent mongol words should be used
in their place so he knew that the
mongolian language is pure than the
turkish language but it's also very
similar
so
they these these peoples the hunik
peoples the turks and the mongols they
called their leaders khans han han it's
not actually k it's not a hard k it's
more like a h han
and the greatest of the hans as we know
it was was chingus ching is khan
he was actually the khan of the khans it
was the khagan
and we had other
other khans such as ogde khan kublai
khan and so on and so forth
so when the mongols
suddenly expanded across eurasia under
the leadership of ching is khan
they essentially
almost
destroyed the islamic world almost
and they conquered baghdad which was
then the seat the center of the islamic
world it was the seat of the islamic
caliphate the sacked baghdad
they sacked the quran and they went far
and wide in
and they essentially started ruling all
these islamic
territories
and eventually the mongols who were
ruling these territories because of
assimilation etc they eventually those
mongols would eventually have converted
to islam and what happened is that all
the rulers at that time of the islamic
world were all khans mongol khans and
therefore this title khan it acquired a
certain extreme prestige
among the islamic peoples
and then slowly slowly they started
using the term
in their own lives and for
themselves so that's how the term khan
entered the islamic world because their
overlords were the great mongol khans
and over time over the centuries it
became kind of a kind of part and parcel
of the islamic world in islamic life
and that's how today you will see lots
of indian muslims pakistani muslims
afghans
etc
using that as as their surname
essentially so that in short is the
history of the khan title
what else do we have let's see some
other questions
i don't know much about the origin of
telugu so can't answer that
uh what else do we have
why does wikipedia support the iron
migration treat theory well
you know what i can answer why i support
certain things if somebody else does it
you need to go ask them
i i don't know really no i i don't know
how how people's minds work
i don't know why people think the way
they do they do so i can only answer for
myself unfortunately
did you read the whole eartha shastra
yes i have read it more than once the
whole arthashastra and i have yet to
digest much of it
it's a very complex and uh
detailed
book
it's not an easy read by any means
right so
it's something you it's something that
you have to read multiple times and
every time you read it even you may even
if you have read it in the past you will
still find so much new information that
you may not have properly
understood before so you'll learn
something new every time you read and
say
similarly
with indian philosophical texts
you may have read the entire
philosophical treaties the what's it
called the
uh the principle openations and yet
every time you reread it you will find
gems that you you may not have noticed
before so that's how it goes
family relations between prophet
muhammad and samudra gupta what are you
smoking dear sir
oh good god
um
let me see some
what else do we have
your views on mahatma gandhi's proposal
to adopt non-violence as national
defense defense policy
yes the best defense policy
is don't defend yourself
it's bound to succeed isn't it
just look at tibet
look at tibet
they believe in non-violence
when the chinese invaded they said
please dear sirs please leave this is
our land please don't be so violent and
so rude and see where they are today the
tibetans
that's what happens when you adopt
non-violence as your official official
defense policy
mr gandhi if he had his way india would
be broken into a thousand pieces to
pieces today
so that's my views
about mr gandhi's proposal
i don't know anything about the various
castes of india so sorry i don't know i
can't answer
okay who was athathur and why is he so
important for the turks
okay so
that's a good question
mustafa kemal atathork is
the
father is is considered to be the father
the father of the modern nation of
turkey and why is it so important it's
because turkey exists essentially only
because of him
otherwise turkey would have been
fragmented and broken off into different
pieces and parceled off to different uh
different countries and different rulers
that's what would have happened so it's
like this
uh
there have been several caliphates there
are the rashidun caliphate and various
umayyad caliphate abbasid
and so on and the last caliphate was the
ottoman caliphate
its capital was constantinople istanbul
right
and the caliph was the ottoman sultan
the head of the ottoman empire
now uh the last great ottoman sultan was
um
suleiman suleiman they call him suleiman
the magnificent
after suleiman all the other khalifs who
came after him with the exception of one
or two they were all degenerates they
were all losers
and their only preoccupation was the
palace politics and the harem
that's their only preoccupation and as a
consequence of that
as a consequence of that
turkey over the years became weaker and
weaker
it still had its huge possessions all
the big territories it had conquered
during the heyday of the ottoman empire
uh large parts of eastern europe
uh syria mesopotamia greece northern
africa and so on and so forth yes
but turkey over time became really weak
and uh it's it's uh
its governance became very rigid its
society became very rigid and in the
19th century turkey was known as the
sikh men
sick man of europe
that's what turkey was looked upon as
now what happened in the late 19th
century that there were many wars turkey
allied itself with the germans
there were there were conflicts with the
with the russian empire and the british
and so on and turkey
essentially became very weak
and it was invaded by various forces the
russians the english etc and some of
them were just a few miles away from the
capital capital city constantinople and
the turkish caliph with ottoman sultan
he
spent his time playing one power against
the other and that's how he remained
independent so it's in the 19th century
that this boy mustafa was born
and he was a brilliant soldier
a very strange man he had no friends and
all that but he was a brilliant soldier
he participated in in
several wars acquitted himself
brilliantly and all that
now in the early 20th century turkey
finally
entered the first world war
and turkey allied itself with germany
which was a mistake so at the end of the
war turkey lost and turkey was
was partitioned essentially by the
victorious powers the western powers and
it was occupied by the western powers
that's what happened
and uh to make a long story short
what mustafa kemal did was that he he
rebelled against this he rebelled
against his own ottoman emperor the
caliph and he uh
he's part of the turkish war of
independence against the western powers
against the bulgarians the greeks and
the ottomans themselves
and to make a long story short he ended
up prevailing at a great risk to his own
life he did all this but he prevailed he
was a brilliant soldier brilliant
commander
and he he won independence for turkey
and he was able to carve out a
reasonably small compact nation of
turkey for the turks and all the other
territories that were part of the
ottoman empire he just let them go he
didn't care about that
and then after the war was over he
became the president for life
essentially of turkey and then he became
an administrator he put away his
military uniform he would never wear it
again and he instituted
all kinds of reforms in turkey he
secularized turkey he banned the burka
and all that all that stuff he
tried to make turkey in the image of a
western nation a modern nation he
modernized turkey he essentially tried
to ban islam from turkey eradicate islam
from turkey
he changed the alphabet from the turkic
from the from the arabic alphabet to a
latinized alphabet and so on and so
forth so he did a lot of things that
completely transformed turkey from a
backward looking 19th century nation to
a modern 20th century republic
right so they the turkish people gave
him the title of ataturk which means the
father of the turks
and even today the turkish politicians
they try to claim the legacy in some way
or the other of ataturk even though
turkey is now going back towards
islamization but still
they try to claim to claim the legacy of
that whatever we are doing
is what ataturk would have wanted that
sort of thing
so that in short is who ataturk was and
why he was so important for the turks i
would say he was one of the greatest
military commanders of all time and one
of the most colossal
leaders of the 20th century for sure a
really
really significant personality of the
20th century
okay
what else do we have
was arunachal pradesh ever part of any
chinese empire on what grounds does
china claim it china has no grounds for
claiming anything
arunachal pradesh has never been part of
any chinese empire
the chinese have had no presence ever in
arunachal pradesh or even really in
tibet
the only basis of the chinese claim on
tibet and all that is
the fact that tibet was a mongolian
protectorate
so it's like this
uh china was
in the
13th
and 14th century i think
china was under the
reign of the yuan dynasty the yuan
dynasty is what's called a conquest
dynasty
it was founded by kublai khan who was a
mongol conqueror and kublai khan
backdated the dynasty to the to his
grandfather ching is khan
so
according to this chronology uh the
first emperor of the of the yuan dynasty
is string is khan the second is oghan
the third is kublai khan and so on so
this was a conquest dynasty it was a
chinese dynasty but
the emperors were all
mongols now the relationship that the
yuan dynasty had with tibet is that of
guru shesha
teacher and student the tibetans were
the teachers
the yuan dynasty the mongols were the
students so essentially all their
priests all their all that brahmin so to
say were tibetan priests tibetan monks
because the mongolians
koble khan had decreed that tibetan
buddhism is like the de facto state
religion of the yuan empire
and the mongols were not very good at
buddhism and all that so they would uh
employ
tibetan masters tibetan gurus as the
officiators of all the ceremonies and
and the and the uh and all that right
and in exchange not an exchange but
because
all their gurus came from tibet that's
why they uh considered tibet
to be their protectorate which means
that it was under mongol protection but
you wouldn't there was no case ever of
mongol soldiers and armies being
stationed in tibet tibet was never under
mongolian occupation
they had the highest respect for tibet
right so the thing is
the mongolians are the highest of
respect for indian culture and they had
imbibed indian culture through tibet
tibet was the intermediary and that's
why they gave the same respect to tibet
as well
so tibet was a mongolian protectorate it
was a protectorate of the yuan dynasty
which was a mongolian dynasty in china
but today the chinese communist party
says that the yuan dynasty which is a
chinese dynasty
it owned tibet
and that's why tibet should be part of
china that is the convoluted logic the
chinese communist party employs today
and then they claim that because the
sixth dalai lama was born in tawang
which is in arunachal pradesh that's why
arunachal pradesh is supposed to be
regarded as south tibet and that's why
that also belongs to china that's the
ridiculous stupid
imbecilic
logic the chinese communist party
employs to further its territorial
uh claims
right so that in brief is the is this is
the story of the so-called chinese claim
on arunachal pradesh which is a lie
harshit says is there a need for india
to change its capital due to pollution
and low visibility in winter if yes what
should be the priorities while choosing
a new capital effect on economy and its
pros and cons
i think it's high time india should dump
delhi as the capital uh delhi has never
been a good capital for india
i mean from the time of indirect etc
it's always been a city of bad luck if
you believe in such things
right and today if you see delhi it's a
congested
deeply
highly polluted city
and all that it's always hostage to all
kinds of nonsensical activities i think
it is high time that india should choose
a new capital india should build a new
capital from
from scratch somewhere
ideally in the heartland of india
somewhere equidistance from all four
corners of india that's the kind of
thing india needs to do i think uh
so so i think the priorities while
teaching choosing a new capital should
be it should be equidistant to all four
corners of india it should be equally
accessible from from from everywhere it
should have excellent connectivity with
the entire country it should be in the
heart of the country not in some extreme
border
region like delhi is about 200
kilometers away from the from the
tibetan border today right so it's easy
for the chinese to target delhi if they
wish to
so that sort of thing also has to be
looked into
so that's what i would say
i think it is not a bad idea at all for
india to choose a new capital to build a
new capital city from from scratch
somewhere in the heartland of india
maybe somewhere in central india
and
make it a city only for administrator
administration no other population is
needed there or only administrators rb
and all that
and all the facilities should be
available there
and yeah so that's a that's a good idea
i would say
how can we evolve our city species
artificially
i don't think it's in you know this
entire thing of playing god and trying
to tinker with your genetic core and
treat a tinker with your bone structure
and all
it is it is not a good idea at all we
simply don't understand how our genes
work let me explain about the human
genome now so now over the the human
genome exists in 23 chapters it's like a
book
a book in 23 chapters 23 pairs of
chromosomes and each pair of chromosome
has a certain bunch of genes in it right
now if you look at the entire genetic
code of human of humans
more than 97 98 percent of this genetic
code
is called uh non-coding dna doesn't code
for any proteins and
some scientists term it as the dark
matter of dna or junk dna and they call
it junk dna because they don't know what
it does it doesn't seem to do anything
that's why they've called it junk dna
those scientists are idiots
nature is parsimonious nothing is wasted
nothing exists for no reason
if there are all these gene sequences in
our genome
and let's say they're not doing anything
right now it doesn't mean they are
useless
they
do serve some function some purpose
maybe we don't understand it today it
means it is our stupidity and our lack
of understanding
rather than the fold of the genome that
it is there right
uh so i would say and you know many
scientists they say that oh it's okay to
use crispr and turn some jeans off and
or turn some jeans on and insert some
genes here and there and
in human beings
and there is there are all these
genetically modified organisms that have
been created new crops with certain
supposedly beneficial properties and all
that you know what
people are tinkering with genes without
really understanding the long-term
downstream effects of all that
and and
most of these effects they are visible
only after 10 20 30 generations
by the time it's impossible to do
anything to change that
so i think we humans have this very
silly tendency to try and play god
especially with genetics and all that
trying to evolve our species
artificially
i think it's a very dangerous thing to
do we know next to nothing of genetics
today 97 98 of our own genome is not
understood at all
and yet we want to tinker with it
just imagine the amount of stupidity
that some scientists have that they
think they can get away with this sort
of thing and actually do some good for
humanity
so i would say that it is not a good
idea
to
play games with nature to play games
with our genetics and with our
physiology
evolution is supposed to happen at its
own pace
of if you look at the history of the
human species we haven't changed much in
the past 100 000 years 1 lakh years
so
if you want to see changes in a species
you have to look at it 100 000 years at
a time or maybe even longer that's the
kind of time it takes for
evolution to become apparent so we have
to be patient we have to let ourselves
evolve
naturally
and
we should desist from trying to make
artificial changes because it's going to
end up costing us in the long run
not us our descendants
yeah i don't know sir i don't know see i
got lots of questions about what is this
cast and what is that cast and what is
their origin i don't know anything about
this i have never been interested in the
study of castes and the origin of this
cast in that cast i don't even know the
origin of my whatever cast it may be i'm
not interested i am a big picture
student of history i look at the history
from from a big picture perspective so i
don't know who the kaistas are and
i'm sure they're very significant people
i'm sure we all are significant in our
own way but i don't know these small
histories i'm not i'm not trying to mean
that these small histories of of small
communities mean that they are not
interesting or important they are all
important but i don't know
sorry
all right
okay here is another wonderful
misconception
so uh the question is did oppenheimer
created create the nucle create the
nuclear bomb using some sanskrit text
you know the nuclear bomb was developed
as a consequence of the manhattan
project
hundreds of physicists were involved in
this it was not one guy who went and
made a nuclear bomb
right
so j robert oppenheimer was the
scientist who was in overall charge of
the product of the of the project the
manhattan project
the project of creating the nuclear bomb
and it was used it was created using the
prese the the principles and the laws of
nuclear physics not some sanskrit text
there is no sanskrit text about a
nuclear bomb or nuclear energy or
quantum mechanics anywhere please
understand this
so the thing is there is this concept
everywhere lots and lots of people
ask me this question but do we have some
secret sanskrit texts that tell that
give you the formula for nuclear bombs
and quantum mechanics and relativity and
all that no no no no no
there is no sanskrit text that i know of
that does any of these things all right
so
what j robert oppenheimer is known for
especially in india
is for quoting the bhagavad-gita when
the
when the first nuclear explosion took
place
so that is something you find among lots
of nuclear lots of physicists especially
theoretical physicists that they are
somehow drawn to
indian philosophy towards sanskrit and
all that
so there is a reason for that that's a
different story
altogether and when he wrote j robert
oppenheimer witnessed the first nuclear
explosion he was reminded of some worse
from the bhagavad-gita i'd i have become
death
or something like that
so that has nothing to do with the
creation of the nuclear bomb right
okay here is another wonderful uh
very common belief about the mahabharata
about the past in india that we got all
okay the question is is
was interspace travel present possible
during the mahabharata arjuna visited
swarga loka to gain power from his
father indra
balrama's father-in-law visited
brahmaloka so how do we know swargaloka
is some other planet in brahmaloka some
other planet
lok doesn't necessarily mean a different
planet
right
so you know what we are taking things
too literally
and we are interpreting all these things
as space travel and and
i don't know what you know what there is
no evidence we had any any such thing
during the mahabharata but indians
believe this
very strongly that we had
we had uh in
interstellar travel and we could go to
different universes and
all things like that there is no
evidence for that unfortunately from my
perspective there is no evidence of that
whatsoever
so that's what i can say
okay what else do we have
can you please name some leader who can
unify india pakistan afghanistan and all
our civilization back and also some
qualities
which leaders need and which points
should he stand on to unifi i don't know
any leader today who can unify the
subcontinent
such a leader will come in the future or
maybe he's already born but i don't know
of any leader who can achieve this of
this feat
today
right so that's what i can say what
qualities do leaders need and all that
well
look back in history and think of the
greatest leaders we have had
those are the qualities a future leader
would need to be able to reunify
the subcontinent think of lord rama lord
krishna
chandragupta maurya
kanishka the great samudra gupta
and raja raj chola rajendra chola etc
think about those leaders and ask
yourself what what qualities they had
those are the qualities we are looking
for
should a leader be the product of the
society or should the society be the
product of the leader in the case of
bharat i would say that a leader in if
if a leader were to emerge who can
transform bharat completely
that leader will not be the product of
the society because the society we live
in today is a mediocre society with very
low standards
so a leader
if a leader were to emerge with the same
characteristics
then that leader would also have low
standards and be a mediocre person look
at most leaders today not all not all
some leaders are good some leaders are
exceptional but the overall majority of
popular of politicians you see today are
mediocre people people with low
standards who are only self-centered who
only care for themselves and who are
very happy to be corrupt
right
so
we need leaders who are who who break
this mold
so
in that case if a great leader does
emerge then he or she will then force
the society to change and become more
like them
you know what they say about cricket
teams
the cricket team if you look at any
cricket team
india australia whatever else
the entire team automatically takes on
the personality of the leader so when
you have a very of the captain
so when you have a very soft spoken
gentle captain the entire team becomes
docile like sheep
on the other door on the other hand if
you have a mad dog captain the entire
team becomes like that they all take on
the personality of their captain
so the same goes for nations also when
you have an extremely confident
vigorous dynamic leader then the whole
nation becomes invigorated like that
and when you have a leader like mr
manmohan singh
you see what happens to the entire
society so i would say that a leader
should always be more exceptional and
greater than the average of the success
of the society
and then the society should become the
product of the leader and and try to
mold themselves in the image of the
leader that is what needs to happen
especially today in india
so this is an excellent question
okay
what other questions do we have let's
see
can we compare modern day's nuclear
weapon to the dwark dwapper yox brahma
astra listen i don't know the
characteristics of the brahmastra i
don't know the details the
specifications
and the blast yield or any such thing so
how do i compare
nuclear weapons come in various sizes
there are standard fission weapons
there are
fission fusion thermonuclear weapons
there are multiple stage weapons there
is a neutron bomb as well
right there are different yields etc
i know how the nuclear physics works in
the case of the
nuclear bombs right
what the brahmastra was i don't know
right how was it activated what what
were the principles behind it i don't
know so then how can i compare the two
i unfortunately cannot compare the two
vikram kumar says would india remain in
one piece by the end of this decade i
don't see why not what makes you think
vikram that we would not remain in one
piece by the end of this decade
i i personally see no reason why india
should not remain in one piece
i think that india in the next 20-30
years is going to be a superpower
god's willing so i don't know why you're
so pessimistic vikram come on come
on uh
how can we
pursue our asi to excavate and find
evidence of our dharmic civilization i
have no hopes in the asi
india needs to
disband the asi and then create a new
professional
archaeological organization from scratch
because the majority of the asi people
are just bureaucrats they just don't
care and if you see all the monuments
temples etc that are under under the
asis care they are being plundered they
have been plundered blind
so i have no hope from the asi
i don't want to pursue or persuade them
to do anything i just want them to be
disbanded
the original objective of the asi which
is of which you may not know it's a
british creation the british created the
asi in the 19th century the original
objective of the asi was to find
pressure so that the the british could
plunder
and take out of the country and put them
in the british museum and various other
western museums so that's what the asi
in some way or the other is still
actually uh enabling and facilitating
and uh you know what i can show you news
report after news report i can show you
hundreds of news reports in which
temples and monuments that are under the
as protection
have been plundered
right
this is all known
so
so i really don't have any hope left for
the esi
how did hanuman reach the sun to eat it
maybe i'm not the right person to ask
this
yeah
maybe i'm not
okay
uh darshan says is plastic really
harmful
to the environment
yes plastic is extremely harmful to the
environment and the simple reason for
that is it is not biodegradable there
are no microbes or natural processes
that can
degrade
and decompose plastic and because of
that plastic remains
present in the
in the environment either in soil or in
water
for decades even for centuries
and what happens is that if it stays in
water for decades in the oceans for
instance in the rivers in lakes etc then
it fragments into smaller and smaller
pieces eventually becoming microscopic
pieces called microplastics and then
what happens is that it ends up in our
food supply and water supply and
whenever you drink water from a bottle
or from the tap or when you eat
something let's say you're eating fish
for instance in japan
then if you examine the the the flesh of
the fish under a microscope you will
find that it is embedded with these
micro plastics
so you are ingesting plastic then it's
going into you and it's going to embed
you in your flesh also and into your
into the
bodies of your of your children and so
on it's going to end up poisoning the
entire
planet in the entire ecosystem that's
how plastic is incredibly harmful to the
environment it is it is choking the
oceans
it is creating these islands of anoxia
it is
descending to the bottoms of the ocean
and choking the place there
uh
and so many other things you know so
it's it's incredibly harmful to the
environment and we are doing nothing
we're doing nothing to stop it it's
terrible
all right where else where else are we
is china hiding its current kovid 19
scenario most most likely it is you know
so the first few months the chinese gave
out some numbers of how many
kovid cases they had that's i'm talking
about the early 2020 early
the first half of 2020 and after a while
they just stopped reporting numbers and
the whole western media just didn't care
they just kept focusing on india and
they did not
say a peep about the fact that the
chinese had stopped giving out any
numbers at all so china can afford to be
completely opec opaque and the western
media won't say a thing about it so yes
i would say that china is certainly
hiding its co current kuwait 19 scenario
we don't know what's going on going on
in china china is always very opaque
that's just how it is
okay
what happened to vishnu sudarshan chakra
did it really turn into stone after
vishnu cursed it
maybe i am not the right person to ask
this
maybe i'm not right
okay
why did the u.s invade latin american
latin american places 41 times in the
20th century
when all these countries were very far
away and not scary for them it's not
they're not scared of anyone
it's about power projection it's about
creating a world order that is
explicitly based on what you say
the u.s is an imperial power please
understand this
the us is a hegemonic power it's an
imperial power
it's the u.s empire that you are living
under whether you know it or not
and that's what the chinese are trying
to replicate today
so the americans did this because the
latin american countries were trying to
do their own thing and how dare they
right
so
that's the whole murky history of the
20th century you you need to really
study it a little bit more to understand
how the world really works
you think the world is a nice free fair
place
rules based order and all that what
nonsense
the 20th century has been the american
century it's been the american imperial
era
and now the american imperial era may
perhaps be under threat
and
if the chinese succeed you're gonna see
a chinese imperial era
so that's just how it is
why greek and indian mythology has so
much of similarities because the greeks
are descendants of ancient very ancient
indians
so the hellenic peoples are the greeks
they are the descendants of the vedic
alina clan
that's why all of their mythology is an
offshoot of indian mythology their
entire pantheon of gods is an offshore
of the indian pantheon of gods
we had diaz pitro
the one of the oldest gods in the vedic
pantheon
who became zeus
peter zeus the greek thunder god
zeus peter in turn became jupiter who is
the
roman thunder god
and we also have perun who is the slavic
thunder god and thor who is the
uh
nordic thunder god these are all
different interpretations of lord indra
that's all it is so
so the uh
the motherland of the
uh indo-european world is india it's
where the entire culture came from and
that's why we have so many similarities
between indian mythology indian culture
etc and all these other indo-european
offshoots european offshores i would say
okay let us take
one or two more questions
how can we stop being mediocre and excel
in our lives by changing our standards
by not tolerating
mediocrity by not tolerating failure in
ourselves and in others that's it
if you change your standards you will
change your life if you
give yourself hives high standards
and you do your best to live live up to
those high standards you will no longer
be mediocre it's very simple
what's the difference between a pulsar
and a magnetor i have at least two
videos on this please check it out you
will see the details in that
okay
i can see so many questions that are
being repeated vimanas i don't know
about vimana so
uh
willie bond says as an american i can
tell you that to read a smedley butler's
war is a racket the people with too much
money have destroyed the american
republic and are imperialist six latin
leaders caught cancer very interesting
thank you for the book reference i'll
certainly check it out
thank you
is the belt and road of china a threat
for for india from the security
perspective yes it is a threat from a
variety of perspectives so what it does
is that it creates an infrastructure for
china to exploit in a variety of ways
it
so it has security implications as well
if the chinese can send trains anywhere
they want at any frequency they like
they can also send soldiers in there and
they can also create these networks of
influence
economic network networks and and so
much more so it is certainly a threat
from india from multiple perspectives
and also from the security perspective
so for instance the
built-in road infrastructure they're
building also goes through tibet and
that's all rail networks right and now
the rail network's there they are
extending those same railway networks to
to
come to almost india's border with tibet
so it's going to enable them to send
soldiers at any time they want so that's
one way to look at it right so it is
certainly a threat
okay
library of alexandria vs library of
naranda both of them got burned which
one contained more knowledge i would say
it was the
library of nalanda and other indian
library that contained much more
knowledge
is kumari kannam true please answer this
sir
there is no evidence that kumari condom
is true
right there's no scientific evidence
there's no geological evidence there is
no
evidence anywhere that this continent
existed
today we can actually
look
beneath the surface of the sea
and we can map
the
ocean bed and that's been done and there
is no trace whatsoever
of any ancient continent that may have
existed in the past
to the south of the peninsula region of
india so
kumari condom is a myth
okay
how to know if the source of knowledge
is genuine
you will you can understand if if
if a source of knowledge is genuine or
not only if you are more knowledgeable
so if you if you are a really well read
person
then you will know if somebody is lying
or trying to fudge something but if you
are not a welded person then how will
you know so the only way to know if some
source of knowledge is genuine or not is
to be extremely well read yourself there
are no shortcuts in life my dear friends
there are absolutely no shortcuts in
life you have to put in the hard work
in order to become knowledgeable and
only then can you tell
if a source of knowledge is genuine or
not
that's how it is
there are no shortcuts in life
all right where else are we what else do
we have
the parallel universe could there be
potentially be ones that contain
doppelgangers of everyone on earth
potentially anything is possible but the
parallel universe theory is
pseudoscience
it's not science it's not physics it's
and the problem is these days even
pseudoscience passes off as science
see a theory that is non-falsifiable is
not a scientific theory
a scientific theory is one that has
that must be falsifiable so if i have a
hypothesis or a theory
then
it should be something that can be
falsified with experiment or with theory
or by putting out a better theory if you
can't do it if you simply cannot falsify
it then it's not science anymore it is
pseudoscience and this entire business
of parallel universes is pseudoscience
because there is no way to disprove
it
we cannot observe anything that is
beyond the observable universe then how
can we even talk about parallel
universes they may possibly exist but
there is no way of proving it or
disproving it
and therefore there's no point even
discussing it right
so yes certainly
there could be potentially any universes
out there that
contain exact replicas of everybody or
not sure it is possible it may also be
possible that there is a teapot in orbit
between mars and jupiter
a red teapot
in orbit between mars and jupiter it's
possible yes
but is there is it really possible i
mean
it's it's can you really falsify it you
can't falsify it and therefore you know
what there's no point discussing it
okay my friends let's take one final
question is there any interesting
question out here
why all mouse have bharatiya mao's
ancestry
bajra is still grown in rajasthan
gujarat i know it is still grown in
rajasthan gujarat but it is no longer a
staple crop india wide right okay now
why do all mice have bharatiya mao's
ancestry that's an interesting question
this is by subita devi so
i haven't studied this in great detail i
had seen a paper a long time ago
it it does appear that all mice in
eurasia seemed to
be descended from an ancestral mouse
that uh lived in india several thousand
years ago
so that is a very interesting point
that's something i need to look into in
more detail but once again it points to
the veracity of the out of india theory
not the aryan invasion theory or aryan
migration tourism picnic theory
nowadays there is even an aryan refugee
theory the thing is
almost all mice across eurasia europe
and asia
seem to have
indian
mouse ancestry which means that ancest
which means that their ancestor was an
indian mouse who lived several thousand
years ago
so that and once again mice don't
migrate on their own they travel with
human beings
surreptitiously they will travel but
they will certainly travel only with
humans
because they are kind of
kind of a domesticated species
so that's interesting yeah so so it
would mean that it indicates
a migration of indians
beyond india and with their travels they
also brought along their their mice
that's what it would indicate
okay
all right i think i'm gonna stop it here
uh
thank you very much everybody for your
questions very interesting questions as
always some some were really interesting
so um
yeah that brings us to an end of this
session and we shall continue next week
and i'm gonna have more interesting
things coming in
in the coming weeks
days and weeks
so thank you everyone once again and
take care and i will see you very soon
bye